Kay Rossman Collection of Alice in Wonderland Memorabilia
Kay Rossman Collection of Alice in Wonderland Memorabilia
1947-2002
Rossman, Kathleen.
18 linear ft.
Collection accumulated by Kay Rossman; extensive and diverse set of items, ranging from Christmas ornaments and figurines to tea sets, clocks, games and record albums.
2740159
Biographical History
Kathleen "Kay" Rossman (1918-2004) was a native of Syracuse, New York, a graduate of Syracuse University, and active throughout her life in university and community volunteer activities. She contributed her time and dedication to many university alumni and fund-raising events and organizations, while her community work included serving on the boards of the Girls Clubs of America, United Way of Central New York, Crouse-Irving Memorial Hospital, Friends of Lorenzo and the Consortium for Childrens Services. She was also a founding member of the Volunteer Center and worked closely with Ruth Colvin, the founder of Literacy Volunteers of America. Her collection of Lewis Carroll books and memorabilia was amassed over many years; she was a member of the Lewis Carroll Society of North America and for nearly ten years she owned and operated a gift shop in Cazenovia named "The Cheshire Cat."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Kay Rossman Collection of Alice in Wonderland Memorabilia consists of an extensive and diverse set of items, ranging from Christmas ornaments and figurines to tea sets, clocks, games and record albums. The inclusive dates given for the collection are approximate, as many items bear no date at all.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items in the collection are in no particular order.
Separated Material
Several hundred books and monographs by and about Lewis Carroll (Charles Lutwidge Dogson) that were part of the collection have been transferred to our Rare Books holdings and cataloged. These include numerous editions of Alice dating back to 1866, as well as titles such as The art of Alice in Wonderland (Stoffel, 1998), The original Alice: from manuscript to Wonderland (Brown, 1997), and The universe in a handkerchief: Lewis Carroll's mathematical recreations, games, puzzles, and word plays (Gardner, 1996). Please refer to and search on "Gift of Kathleen W. Rossman" to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- Children's; Carroll, Lewis, 1832-1898 -- Collectibles.; Carroll, Lewis, 1832-1898 -- Alice in wonderland -- Collectibles.; Carroll, Lewis, 1832-1898 -- Through the looking glass -- Collectibles.; Rossman, Kathleen.; Alice (Fictitious character: Carroll) -- Collectibles.; Cheshire Cat (Fictitious character: Carroll) -- Collectibles.; Mad Hatter (Fictitious character) -- Collectibles.; Audiocassettes.; Calendars (documents); Candlesticks.; Clippings (information artifacts); Coloring books.; Correspondence.; Character dolls.; Character toys.; Exhibition catalogs.; Figurines.; Jigsaw puzzles.; Long-playing records.; Paper dolls.; Photographs.; Picture postcards.; Scripts (documents); Sound recordings.; Posters.; Programs (documents); Videocassettes.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Kay Rossman.
Inventory
- Memorabilia
  - Alice in Wonderland book of ornaments, Metropolitan Museum of Art, added 8/2002 (Box 1)
  - "Nest of Alice" characters, painted wooden dolls (Box 1)
  - Mobile with tree centerpiece, created by Su Gay, features Cheshire Cat, Alice, and White Rabbit. All pieces are wooden. Characters are decorative in cloth and painted, except for the tree. (Box 1)
  - Actual Chestnut from the Christ Church Deanery Garden, Oxford University, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Alice china flower container "The Mad Tea Party" (Box 1)
  - Cheshire cat metal hand bell (Box 1)
  - The Mad Hatter miniature jigsaw puzzle (Box 1)
  - Alice Down the Rabbit Hole Llandudno metal pin (Box 1)
  - Alice miniature crown in box (Box 1)
  - Stuffed cloth Alice hanging ornament (Box 1)
  - Handmade decorative tree ornaments, in the shape of eggs, 5 items (Box 1)
  - Orange belt with 6 picture frame pins of Alice in Wonderland (Box 1)
  - Bronze Alice character, the White Rabbit, by Heredities (Box 2)
  - Lavender Alice doll by Cuckoobird (Box 2)
  - Metal pencil boxes, 4 items (Box 2)
  - Tweedle Dee/Tweedle Dum figurine/ornament, by A Company of Friends, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Alice figurine/ornament, by A Company of Friends, 1979 (Box 2)
  - White Rabbit figurine/ornament, by A Company of Friends, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Queen of Hearts' Herald figurine/ornament, by A Company of Friends, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Alice doll,12", on metal stand (Box 2)
  - Cheshire Cat door knockers, brass, 2 ite,s (Box 2)
  - Cheshire Cat candle holder, brass (Box 2)
  - "She Must Go by Post, as She's Got a Head on Her, Alice, North Dakota," by Virginia Godfrey Langlois, 1984; booklet (Box 2)
  - Key chain and necklace with images from "Alice's Adventures in Wonderland" from the Year of the Child (Box 2)
  - British Post Office mint stamps from the Year of the Child, 2 packs (Box 2)
  - Hallmark Keepsake ornament "Alice Meets the Cheshire Cat" (Box 3)
  - 2 Alice tin boxes (3 ½" X 2 ¾" X 2 ¾") (Box 3)
  - Large "Alice Through the Looking Glass" tin box (Box 3)
  - Ceramic Cheshire Cat created by Christina Gray (Box 3)
  - Tin "Alice in Wonderland" box with clock (Box 3)
  - Original Alice Clock by Roger Lascelles Clocks of London (Box 3)
  - Packet of materials about Christina Gray's Cheshire Cat and other Carroll merchandise (Box 3)
  - Round biscuit tin (Box 4)
  - Framed map of Oxford, England (Box 4)
  - Stained glass Cheshire Cat (Box 4)
  - Hanging plate of Alice and the White Rabbit with wooden stand (Box 4)
  - Oval stained glass Cheshire Cat (Box 4)
  - Stained glass rectangular Alice in Wonderland scenes with chains, 6 items (Box 4)
  - Alice in Wonderland plates, 3 items (Box 5)
  - Set of Alice in Wonderland wooden figurines, 13 items (Box 5)
  - Alice in Wonderland tea set, includes a teapot, 2 cups and 2 saucers (Box 5)
  - Alice in Wonderland mug (Box 5)
  - Stuffed Alice in Wonderland character ornaments, 3 items (Box 6)
  - Mad Hatter's Tea Party tea towel (Box 6)
  - The MacMillan Alice Address Book, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Alice in Wonderland silk scarf (Box 6)
  - Length of Alice in Wonderland fabric, 1⅔ yards X 48" (Box 6)
  - Screen prints
    - Alice and the Caterpillar (Box 6)
    - Mad Hatter's Tea Party (Box 6)
  - Alice in Wonderland jigsaw puzzle (Box 6)
  - Alice in Wonderland soap collection (Box 7)
  - Alice and the White Rabbit night light (Box 7)
  - Package of Alice in Wonderland postcards, note cards, and bookmarks (Box 8)
  - Reading the Mind by Lewis Carroll, boxed, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Eight or nine Wise Words about Letter Writing by Lewis Carroll, boxed, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Alice's Flip Book (Box 8)
  - Alice in Wonderland paper doll by Tim Tierney, Dover Little Activity Books (Box 8)
  - Package of Alice in Wonderland postcards, 12 items (Box 8)
  - Alice in Wonderland Notched Card Construction and Building Set (Box 8)
  - Bag of items from Alice's shop in Oxford, including catalog (Box 8)
  - Alice in Wonderland stickers, 2 packages (Box 8)
  - Alice in Wonderland jigsaw puzzles, 6 items (Box 8)
  - Box of animals from Wonderland Writing Papers (Box 8)
  - Large sheet of embossed cut-out paper dolls from Alice in Wonderland (Box 8)
  - Books on audiocassette
    - Alice in Wonderland by Lewis Carroll, read by Marvin Miller and Jane Webb, Cassette Book Company (Box 9)
    - Through the Looking Glass by Lewis Carroll, read by Dana Craig, Cassettet Book Company, 1983 (Box 9)
    - Alice in Wonderland and Through the Looking Glass by Lewis Carroll, read by Alan Bennett, BBC Young Collection, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Through the Looking Glass by Lewis Carroll, read by Richard and Marilyn Sharine, Cassette Productions, 1981; 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Alice's Adventures in Wonderland by Lewis Carroll, read by Richard and Marilyn Scharine, Casette Productions, 1981; 2 tapes (Box 9)
    - Lewis Carroll's Songs: Original Melodies and Victorian Verses, Syndicat du Wonderland, 1986 (Box 9)
  - TLC Great Books video of Alice in Wonderland, 1 videocassette (Box 9)
  - Porcelain dolls of the White Rabbit, the Queen of Hearts, the Mad Hatter, Alice (Box 9)
  - AB Bookman's Weekly, Special Children's Book Issue, November 16, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Photograph of Alice dolls (Box 10)
  - Description of "Alice's Adventures in Wonderland" exhibit by the Osborne Collection of Children's Books, Toronto Public Library, May 11, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Description of "Alice 125: Pictures and Conversation" exhibit at the Enoch Pratt Free Library, Baltimore, Maryland, April 1987 (Box 10)
  - Plastic bag of miscellaneous paper items related to Alice in Wonderland (Box 10)
  - Samples of full text online: U-M Fantasy and Science Fiction website (Box 10)
  - Package of catalogs, articles, and materials related to Alice in Wonderland (Box 10)
  - New York Times crossword puzzle (Box 10)
  - Alice in Wonderland coloring books, 2 items (Box 10)
  - Sir John Tenniel's Alice: 16 Prints in Colour (Box 10)
  - Black and white illustrations from Alice in Wonderland and Through the Looking Glass, 14 items (Box 10)
  - Paper bags from Alice's Lewis Carroll's Sheep Shop, 83 St. Aldate's Oxford (Box 10)
  - Alice in Wonderland cutout note cards from the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2 boxes (Box 10)
  - Photographs from Cleota Reed to Kay Rossman (Box 11)
  - Lewis Carroll's Birthplace Trust brochure, 2 copies (Box 11)
  - Playbill, Alice in Wonderland (Box 11)
  - Folder of miscellaneous articles, pamphlets, magazines, and other materials (Box 11)
  - Smithsonian Magazine, August 1892 (Box 11)
  - Wake Forest Magazine, December 1997 (Box 11)
  - Disney's Alice in Wonderland Activity Pad (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers about Alice in Wonderland (Box 11)
  - Queen Victoria's Alice in Wonderland (Box 11)
  - Cohen, Morton N. Typescript of talk given at Christ Church, 1982 (Box 11)
  - Carroll brochures (Box 11)
  - Postcards and bookmarks (Box 11)
  - Johnson, Linda, correspondence; 26 letters (Box 11)
  - Newspaper articles (Box 11)
  - Children's books and illustrated books (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper and journal articles (Box 11)
  - Magazines with articles about Alice in Wonderland (Box 12)
  - Conferences
    - LCSNA visit to Christ Church, Oxford England, 1982 July 26-31
      - Correspondence (Box 13)
      - Exhibition Catalogs (Box 13)
      - Photographs (Box 13)
      - Notes and memorabilia (Box 13)
    - International Lewis Carroll Conference, 1st, Oxford, 1989 July 27-30
      - Exhibition Catalogs (Box 13)
    - International Lewis Carroll Conference, 2nd, 1994 June 9-12
      - Correspondence
      - Programs (Box 13)
      - Auction catalog (Box 13)
      - Exhibition catalogs (Box 13)
      - Photographs (Box 13)
      - Notes and miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Carroll Foundation (Australia)
    - Correspondence (Box 13)
    - See: Conferences 1989 July 27-30 Printed material, Exhibition catalogs
    - Printed Material (Box 13)
  - Lewis Carroll Society (Daresbury Cheshire England), Lewis Carroll Birthplace Trust
    - Fundraising (Box 13)
    - Miscellany (Box 13)
    - Constitution (Box 13)
    - Membership (Box 13)
    - Publications lists (Box 13)
    - Miscellany (Box 13)
  - Lewis Carroll Society of North America (LCSNA), 1978-1995; correspondence, programs, announcements; 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Lewis Carroll Society of North America, West Coast Chapter (Box 13)
  - Adaptations
    - Cinematic announcements (Box 14)
    - Literary (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous performances (Box 14)
    - Musical
      - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
      - Nonsense Songs from Alice in Wonderland, circa 1908 (Box 14)
    - Theatrical
      - Programs (Box 14)
      - K. Rossman version of Grassie script used for book club presentation (Box 14)
      - Isobel Grassie script, circa 1952 (Box 14)
      - Clarke, Henry Savile, Stage production of "Alice" (Box 14)
  - Alice in North Caroll-ina (Box 14)
  - Advertisements and brochures (Box 14)
  - Alice in Wonderland Collectables, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Carroll Centenary, UK (Box 14)
  - Collector's notes, index cards (Box 14)
  - Exhibition programs (Box 14)
  - The Hunting of the Snark (Box 14)
  - Illustrators of Alice in Wonderland, clippings (Box 14)
  - Keepsakes (Box 14)
  - Lectures, talks and sermons (Box 14)
  - Lewis Carroll pending items (Box 14)
  - Lewis Carroll Program, Kappa Kappa Gamma, November 31, 1990 (Box 14)
  - Lewis Carroll Society of North America "Alice in New York", March 27, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Lovett book draft (Box 14)
  - Magazine and newspaper clippings and cartoons (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous articles and advertisements (Box 14)
  - News articles, 1970's and 1990's (Box 14)
  - Note cards and postcards (Box 14)
  - Publication announcements and book advertisements (Box 14)
  - Pogany, Willy (illustrator) (Box 14)
  - K. Rossman personal materials (Box 14)
  - K. Rossman personal recognition (Box 14)
  - Figure renditions by Diane Smoler (Box 14)
  - Tenniel paper, Social Art Club, February 10, 1976 (Box 14)
  - Wonderland-Spiegel (Box 14)
  - Alice through the Looking Glass tin (Box 15)
  - Figurines of Alice, the Mad Hatter, and the Queen of Hearts (Box 15)
  - Rubber stamp, "Kathleen W. Rossman Collection Relating to Lewis Carroll" (Box 15)
  - Metropolitan magnets, Alice in Wonderland (Box 15)
  - Rubber stamps (Box 15)
  - Stained glass panel (Box 15)
  - Article, "Christmas with Lewis Carroll," New York Times Magazine, December 20, 1981 (Box 16)
  - LIFE magazine with Alice on the cover, April 28, 1947 (Box 16)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 16)
  - The Newberry Library calendar with Sir John Tenniel's illustrations adapted for The Nursery ‘Alice', 1982 (Box 16)
  - Alice-in-Wonderland Spin Game (Box 16)
  - Figurines, assorted (Box 16)
  - Cheshire Cat backscratcher, bronze (Box 17)
  - Tote bags, assorted (Box 17)
  - Posters, assorted (Box 17)
  - Small note pad (Box 17)
  - Posters, oversize
  - Framed etching of the Mad Hatter
  - Large calendars, 2 items
  - Vinyl records
    - David Del Tredici's Final Alice with Barbara Hendricks, The Chicago Symphony, and Sir Georg Solti, includes newspaper clippings
    - Through the Looking-Glass with Joan Greenwood as Alice and Stanley Holloway
    - Lewis Carroll's Alice in Wonderland adapted and produced by Douglas Cleverdon with Jane Asher as Alice, 2 copies with different album art
    - Through the Looking Glass read and sung by Cyril Ritchard, original musical score by Alec Wilder, played by the New York Woodwind Quintet, "including a facsimile volume of the rare 1872 first edition of the book"
    - Alice's Adventures in Wonderland read and sung by Cyril Ritchard, original musical score by Alec Wilder, played by the New York Woodwind Quintet, "including a facsimile volume of the rare 1872 first edition of the book", 2 copies